and so my plan since we already have
momentum here is we've been reviewing
the a big idea of probability
distributions and one example we can go
to is what's called a a coin biased coin
so not all coins have to be
50/50 there can be a particular
probability that is not one half that
the pro that the coin winds up on heads
and this is a nice starter example for
some of the concepts that we might want
to look at and the first concept that we
can look at for a single
distribution is what's called Shannon
entropy now if you look at the
definition of Shannon entropy on
Wikipedia which I will I will look at
but not pull
up the formula in is not too hard to
calculate and talk
about what happens here in just a
second but
the formula for the probability
distribution um is we're going to sum
over all of the possible
events so X small X is a single
event and big X is the sample
space which is all possible events that
could
occur and we're going to add the we're
going to do a
minus in
front I don't know why Shannon entropy
is commonly written with h maybe someone
else does but h of X big X X because it
belongs to the space is negative the sum
of over all possible events of the
probability of each event times the log
of the probability of each
event so maybe this looks terrible
symbolically maybe it doesn't um let's
see what that looks like with a 50/50
coin so if we look at a 50/50 Fair coin
then the probability of
of H is
0.5 probability of tails is
0.5 this H and T are examples of the
small X so our sample space our big X
overall would be that we have two events
heads or
tails and each event has a probability
such that the probabilities add up to
one so if I want to calculate um it's
less than ideal that H is reused here so
maybe I'll make this be a script H to
make it more
distinct so if I want to look at
the Shannon entropy of this
distribution I'm just going to take
the probab
times so it's going to be
minus as it starts with the minus it's
going to be
0.5
Times log of
0.5 because I'm taking care of the H
here and then I have to do the same
thing for the T which is
0.5
Times log of
0.5 and we can calculate that
I don't know what log of 0.5 is off hand
can anyone calculate this and tell me
what the number
is if not I can do it but yall are
welcome to jump in
just now it seems to be about negative
0.693 you're saying that's for the
overall
number oh sorry no just log of
0.5 I see okay yeah now I got you um and
then it turns out miraculously that when
you calculate because this is you know
dist distribution you get Negative log
of 0.5 so this number is about
0693 and okay so that's a number and I
guess the question is what does that
tell
us well what I feel might be helpful is
to calculate this not for this single
one but now for arbitrary
probability so
let's now say we look at any coin
any
coin and we're going to look at
probability its heads and probab
probability its tails so I'm going to
use so I'm going to use X for the
probability that we have
heads and I don't know what x is X is a
number it tells me how biased the coin
is towards
heads and then I'm going to look at the
one minus t or 1 minus X which is the
probability of Tails so this is a biased
coin and how biased it is is determined
by
X and we can do the same thing we just
did let's call this
um Shannon
entropy of our I'm going to
use capital X subb
and b stands for bias and because I
decided to
use B here I'm actually going to use B
here because I I don't want to overload
these X's especially when they tend to
look so much
alike so this will
be probability of heads is B probability
of tails is one minus B
so now I
have negative and I'm going to add
up B
[Music]
* log of
B+ 1us
btimes log of 1us B
now this depends on B so I can't come up
with a single number here but I can make
a plot
of different things this could look like
and let's see what it looks
like e
share the
screen but not destroy the Whiteboard so
let me see can I save this
so now I'm going to look at the plot of
this
and I want to look at this from what's
the smallest value that b could possibly
be if B is the probability
that the coin comes up heads
well zero put that it could be zero and
it could be at most one there's actually
a little bit of weirdness here because
we can't take log of zero I have to come
back to that
uh but
I'm going to plot this and to see what
it looks
like unfortunately now I have to
switch to
X and probably get away with not doing
that just make
that menion okay
and I need a negative
here and you have to be careful about
which
log Bas we using to be
consistent okay this is kind of
interesting this is the graph of Shannon
in P so
[Music]
the yes
um would something so something at zero
is actually a no
no
uh 0 times natural log of zero is
undefined and
uh there's a a convention that people
make because in math how are things
defined they're not defined you know
they're defined by us essentially by
social convention so natural log of zero
is an undefined
quantity
um so what you do to work around that is
you just Define that to be zero and
you'll see people do this colon equals
to say hey I am defining this to be this
and it turns out it doesn't cause any
problems uh when you're when you're
really close to zero it's not a problem
it's only a problem right at
zero and that's why you see you see that
already when you scroll in here close to
b equals z so this is on the x- axis the
probability that the coin comes up heads
and then on the y- axis I have the
Shannon entropy for that distribution of
coin
values so what do you see here
is the probability of the coin being
heads approaches 0. five or you know the
the probability of the you know the
distribution p and then one minus B the
more similar they are the less
information we have well the more
similar they are the greater the entropy
of the distribution and perhaps we can
then interpret that as saying the less
certain we are about
uh what
the uh what the bias of the coin is but
then
again we know the Bu The
Coin so this is definitely a a maximum
value at
0.5 and uh you said something
about and it it's shaped like a parabola
it's
um oh
concave down the entire
way and you said can
you okay you said something that had a
lot in it and I if you'd be willing to
just repeat it about um this
interpretation of why the maximum
Shannon entropy occurs when the
probabilities are equal or what that
what that just pops into your
mind yeah well I I guess colloquially um
you know entropy is is a measure of the
spread of a probability distribution so
visually if we were to plot say the
probability distribution at uh P equal
.5 we'd have two bars of height .5 and
they'd be kind of
exactly uh spread out you know whereas
if we had p p equal like one then we'd
have a massive bar at one and a tiny
non-existent bar at zero and that would
not be very you know quote unquote
spread out so P equal 0.5 is where the
distribution is is the most spread out
so that that then corresponds to the the
greatest
entropy okay okay so the greatest
entropy occurs and you're saying that we
would have a a
bar looks like this
HT and each of them has a height of
0.5 the two heights are equal and that's
what maximum intri looks like
versus absolute
certainty
of um Tails let's say or yeah absolute
certainty of
Tails I think actually the way I set
this up IE is backwards this
is because I said that b was the
probability of heads so let me be
consistent to not confuse people um so
then it's probability of heads is
1.0 okay um
then that has zero
entropy and you said that clo entropy is
a spread of the
distribution and that's I'm totally okay
with that um I'd also say it's the
uncertainty about individual events
or uh again being collo colloquial How
likely am I to
be how good a strategy is guessing one
of the
values uh so if I look here where B is
equal to
0.9 that corresponds
to the probability of heads is
0.9 and the probability of t is
0.1 so I expect that if I say heads I'm
going to be right most of the time in
other words I feel I have a lot of
information about what the next coin
flip is likely to be and if I use a
guessing strategy where I guess heads
all the time then I'm probably going to
be right most of the time right and so I
I have a good approximation strategy
does that make
sense I hope it does I know that we're
going through this slowly and carefully
um but I feel it's good to build
things
[Music]
so maybe we could look also at what the
just the standard Wikipedia treatment of
this is so
what does it say about
entropy I'm going to take a screenshot
of this
so it says in information Theory the
entropy of a random variable is the
average level of information surprise or
uncertainty inherent to the variable's
possible
outcomes given a discrete random
variable X and a discrete random
variable X here is the same thing as
what I was calling a discrete
probability
distribution which takes values in the
set X that's
sample
space then we calculate the entropy like
this we do have a choice in the base
of the logarithm so if we use the
natural log we get what are called
Nets if we use the base
two we
get bits
the motivation for
this is coming from communication Theory
Shannon was working on um creating
signals to send be worked for telephone
company he was working on
creating
uh yeah he was working on creating a way
of compressing information to send it
and then measuring how good a job had
been
done so there's actually something else
U that pops up here that we used before
or could have defined even before we
jumped into
entropy which was the information
content which is the negative logarithm
of the probability of an
event or the surprisal it's also
called so in entropy measures the
entropy is a weighted average of
surprisal entropy is an expected or
average amount of information compay
conveyed by identifying the outcome of a
random trial it's how much
information we're going to get every
time we flip the coin
so I want to go back and pull this into
kback leer
Divergence pack ler Divergence was
originally called relative
entropy and that's why it's important to
have some sense of entropy before going
into cobc webler because it's based on
entropy let's take a moment and look at
this
formula
the just this has popped up in chapter
this pops up in chapter two of the
textbook here we're going to be given
two probability distributions and what
I'd like to do to make this very
concrete is to imagine that we have two
biased coins or maybe a bias coin and a
Fair
coin so I'm going to say let's just say
p is a Fair coin 50%
heads Q is a biased coin which has B
percent heads probability of
B of course you can do this for any
distribution um any pair of probability
distributions do you see how this looks
like the formula
for Shannon entropy
if Q ofx were equal to one and this were
made negative so the original formula
was very similar to
this but it had a negative in front of
the summation and there was no Q of X in
the
denominator let's calculate the KL
Divergence for two
coins um
so to do
this I will
need a biased coin would anyone be
willing to create a biased coin for me
which all you have to do is specify the
probability of
heads s okay why not what a great you
said
7 yeah Okay cool so let's have P our
first probability distribution be fair
which is just heads and tails are both
50% and then my biased coin Q is going
to be that probability of heads is
7 so now I'm going to calculate the Rel
entropy or the kak leader Divergence of
and the order does matter this is not
symmetric so I'm going to go P
first and I'm going to add
up over my
events
the P of x
time
log of p ofx
over Q
ofx so this is going to be summing over
two things one that corresponds to H and
one that corresponds to T so we're going
to have
0.5 so first let's work with the H part
0 0.5 * log
of 0.5
/
0.7
plus 0.5 now I'm going to work on the T
part so P of this is p of
T times I'm going to do
log of
0.5 /
0.3 and I do not know what those are off
hand uh the first term looks something
like
0.336
okay is that the final oh go ahead no
that's just the first
term I guess I could give you the final
it's uh are we missing a a negative sign
in front of the first ter no I don't
think so
um do you see that in the formula I
don't see any negatives in the formula
oh sorry this is K division I'm just
yeah yeah no problem absolutely so the
final thing is about
0.59 I
believe okay cool
um does anyone else agree I mean
basically I'm just asking if someone
will type this into wol from alpha or oh
actually uh that's
incorrect that's negative
0.08 I missed a minus sign let's see why
is there a minus
sign uh math.log 0.5 on
0.7 I
see um oh and I missed I missed a 0.5 as
well sorry I'm causing all kinds of
trouble here it's okay uh 0.5 times
that is that and then 0.5 times that is
that I'm gonna stop being ask you I'm
gonna stop being lazy and we'll both
check
it positive 0.08 is what I'm getting now
I get that get that as well
0.0 um one of the sanity tests we can do
is that this number should always be
positive and okay so for these two
specific coins cack leler Divergence is
0.08 um couple of things to say about
the about the K Divergence or the
relative
entropy one is whenever you calculate it
it should be
positive or it should at least be um
non- negative and it will be zero if and
only
if if and only if the uh distributions
are exactly the same yes
yeah so some facts here
a l Divergence
is I'm just going to call it relative
entropy relative entropy is always
greater than equal to
zero it will be
zero if the two distributions are the
same and then some
interpretations it's a it's like a
distance
uh it's not a metric in the mathematical
sense
for one thing it's not
symmetric
the
but it is intended to give an idea of
how similar two probability
distributions
are so based on that intuitive
interpretation if I picked another
biased coin that was closer to being
fair
um what would you expect to happen with
this
value and I'm about to make a mistake
I'm about to say it has a larger or
smaller relative
inry um
it's yeah so I'm about out of time on
this session and then I have a a short
break that so the the big idea here is
uh K
Divergence so we
have sub KL of P
e parallel lines
Q is equal to the
sum this is true for discret and we
replace it with an integral if it's
continuous but for now let's do p of
x
[Music]
times
log P of X over Q
ofx so we calculated this where P was a
Fair coin
and now we want to calculate it and we
calculated where P was a Fair coin and Q
was a
specific bias distribution that had a
70% chance of coming up
heads oh okay um so let's go ahead and
calculate this bit again uh so this
would
be 0.5 times
log of 0.5 /
0.7
plus 0.5 * the log of 0.5 /
0.3 this what does log mean is different
depending on who you are for a
mathematician it's almost always the
case that log means natural log log BAS
e for an engineer they tend to
prefer log base
10 and computer
scientists usually often use log base
too and it doesn't matter in terms of
the qualitative types of information
that we get but it makes a big
difference in terms of the actual
numbers so probably I will have this
habit that I need to be careful about of
always is writing log for natural
log
um so
the now what we'd like to do is do this
more General calculation and so if just
qualitatively based
on the little bit we know so far about K
Divergence
if we have
a if we had a coin that was more
biased um would we expect the KL
Divergence to
increase or decrease
so we have one guess for increase let's
see what happens um now we're going to
do this with P being the Fair
coin and Q being even more biased
towards heads so let's say this has a
90% chance of being
heads and let calculate
so we're going to add up the head
is
0.5
time log of
0.5 /
0.9
and pale is 0.5 * log of 0.5 5 * 0.1
let's say that's equal
to I'll calculate this
[Music]
out okay so I got
0.51 I'm using here the natural log
um if you use log base 10 you'll get a
smaller
number
but so originally it was smaller than
0.51 so the K Divergence increased so
our guess was right and that matches
intuitively the fact that K Divergence
should be closer to zero for more
similar probability distributions and
it's actually intended to measure in
some sense how similar the two
probability distributions
are so what we could do is what we did
before we could look at this for an
arbitrary biased coin with a bias of
B
and the formula then would be for an
arbitrary coin if I just take the same
formula
and replace this
with b and this with one minus B then I
can replace this 0.9
here with b and this 0.1
with one minus B now this is going to be
a function of B so we have one number in
we can input the bias of our coin
towards
heads and we can output the KL
Divergence from a Fair
coin I'm sorry I need to be precise in
my terminology we output the K
Divergence between the Fair coin and the
bias coin
and so we can plot this I'm going to
instead of using the B I'm going to use
the small X my variable name but our
function here that depends on one value
would be output Y is equal to
0.5 time log of 0.5 / B which is the
head's part plus
0.5 time the log
of 0.5 / 1 minus B um except I'm going
to call this x instead of B
just because X and Y are the more common
variable names so X is the bias of the
coin and Y will be the K
Divergence so if I plot
that let's see what it looks like
kind of interesting plot let's see it
so if I look at this part where the bias
is the bias of the biased coin is 0.5
it's actually a Fair coin here the K is
equal to
zero when the coin is actually
fair and then what you see is as the
coin becomes biased and One Direction or
another towards heads or tails the kale
Divergence begins to blow
up so that K Divergence would actually
be approaching
Infinity for a
totally um for a coin that was totally
biased and always landed on H heads or
always landed on
Tails so this gives us another
qualitative tool of
understanding uh how the K Divergence
depends on the specific distributions
that we're looking
at now my goal in doing this was to make
this more concrete
um chapter
the first mention of math is in the
book not the appendix but the actual
book
itself jumps from the sum rule for
probability it's one of the first things
you would learn in probability two k
Divergence in the space of about two
pages and that's that's not
impossible but I think it helps to have
this comfort of going through and saying
CH Divergence is something that it is
actually possible to compute that you
could compute successfully correctly and
now we can apply this to any probability
distribution that we want to look at
including uh continuous ones which would
just require the definition of entropy
and the kale Divergence require passing
from a sum to an integral at that point
but philosophically it's the same that
we are calc using calculations based on
the probabilities that we know to
determine how similar or dissimilar
these two probability distributions
are youall have any questions thoughts
or comments about that that's all that I
had
prepared and if I had to do this over I
would start with
surprise as the negative logarithm of
probability and then go to entropy and
then go to k
Divergence U surprisal
it's the negative logarithm of
probability do y'all have any questions
or thoughts that y'all want to add or
share at this point I'm always open to
hear
what things can we do on our own to
strengthen our understanding of what you
covered today
um I think that doing
some
calculations I know that people want to
skip calculations sometimes and say I'm
just focusing on the big picture but
often doing the calculations
builds belief that you do understand
it so perhaps we can create a sequence
of notes or exercises that will enable
people to practice and see what they
understand I think that would be the
best um I'm happy to to look at others
resources and I think we can also create
some of our
own the second thing
is just keep
engaging
um it's possible that some people are
naturally good at this but the people
I've known who were good at it spent
time on it
and even if you don't intend
to do calculation intensive work in the
future it can still be like a kind of
mental yoga that can support you in
other
ways do those question do those help at
all
uh cool great we've actually not done
Bas rule but
uh
the which would be something else that
we could do but I'm going by what I see
first in the actual text of the book and
the first thing it jumps into
is jumps pretty quickly into is this K
Divergence so getting comfortable with
that might be
helpful cool well I really appreciate
yall coming out um I am afraid I will
have to miss next Tuesday I might look
at doing next Friday as a
makeup but I'd like to uh put together
some materials on this and then we can
y'all can certainly
Aid in that and looking forward to see
what happens and appreciate yall coming
out all right take care bye